Francisco Torralba, PhD, CFA

francisco.torralba@gmail.com - (312)480-8705 - www.linkedin.com/in/franciscotorralba/

Employment eligibility: U.S. citizen, authorized to work for any U.S. employer.

Professional economist with 11 years of experience in finance and macroeconomics. Experienced using advanced statistics and econometrics and communicating to expert and non-expert audiences, and proficient with multiple computer languages. Independent, self-motivated, and restless learner.

EDUCATION

Ph.D., Economics, University of Chicago, Chicago, IL	Aug. 2010
M.A., Economics, University of Chicago, Chicago, IL	Jun. 2008
B.S., Economics, Universitat Pompeu Fabra, Barcelona, Spain	Jun. 1999

EXPERIENCE

Morningstar Investment Management Inc., Chicago, IL

Director of Research

Jan. 2022 - Feb. 2022

- · Replicate, design and execute systematic, quantitative equity strategies and portfolios.
- · Promote research, analysis, and data collection best practices.
- · Develop training sessions on quantitative methods and economics, for mid-level and junior analysts.

Senior Economist

Jan. 2015 - Dec. 2021

- · Created quantitative assessment of the macroeconomic vulnerability ("country risk") of 30 countries. Used multivariate kernel density in R to produce nine indicators of vulnerability per country.
- · Estimated the *long-run* equity risk premium (ERP), using both cash-flow-discount models and timeseries models, working with both Matlab and Python. The models were then combined, mitigating model uncertainty.
- · Forecast EBIT per share, at the one-year horizon, for a cross section of companies, using company-level fundamentals and analysts' forecasts and working with R. Compared the out-of-sample forecasting performance of random forest with those from traditional panel-data models.
- · Estimated the co-movement of revenue of MSCI industries and industry groups with global economic activity, using Stata, as an assessment of the cyclicality/defensiveness of industries based on revenue.
- · Replicated an existing model of term premiums from the zero-coupon curve in Python, informing internal users about the drivers of sovereign bond yields for six countries.
- · Developed model to predict macroeconomic crises using machine learning and traditional methods.

Economist (Ibbotson Associates, Inc.)

Jun. 2010 - Dec. 2014

- · Owned and improved time series forecast of inflation for a client, and delivered monthly updates.
- · Independently wrote quarterly commentary on global economic outlook and financial trends, directed to both our external audience (clients) and internal users (portfolio managers and asset class leaders).
- \cdot Presented to internal and external audiences, including at our annual conference, on the outlook for the economy and the markets.
- · Supervised intern for four months.

Nuveen Asset Management, Chicago, IL

Research Analyst

Sep. 2008 - Jun. 2009

- · Rated credit quality of municipal bonds in the healthcare and senior living sectors.
- · Analyzed financial statements of hospitals and retirement facilities to assess the sustainability of existing and new debt liabilities, and the current pricing of corporate bonds relative to comparable issuers.
- · Met schedule of bond issuer reviews per month.
- · Led economics committee that produced outlook for growth, inflation, and interest rates.

University of Chicago, Chicago, IL

Research Assistant and Teaching Assistant

2003 - 2007

- · Empirical investigation on the importance of precautionary saving, for prof. A. Lusardi.
- · Empirical investigation of the profitability of investments in real estate, for prof. P. Willen.
- · TA for classes in: macroeconomics (3), microeconomics, econometrics, and labour economics.

KPMG, Barcelona, Spain

Senior Accountant

Sep. 1999 - Jul. 2001

- · Participated in accounting audits of financial entities (banking, insurance, and mutual funds).
- · Prepared, analyzed, and consolidated financial statements.

BBVA, corporate banking office, Barcelona, Spain

Summer intern

Jun. 1998 - Sep. 1998

· Discounting of trade bills.

SKILLS

Econometrics/quantitative analysis

Time series modeling and forecasting; prediction of binary dependent variables with small samples; analysis of panel data with cross-sectional dependence; random forests and penalized regression; estimation of Bayesian models; forecast combination; assembling and updating customized data sets from public data feeds. Visualization and presentation of data via R, MS Excel, LATEX(beamer), and MS PowerPoint.

Computer languages and software

R, Matlab/Octave, Python, Stata, LATEX, R Markdown, MS Office. Beginner in SQL, Tableau, and Julia.

Natural languages

Native speaker of Spanish and Catalan; intermediate French.

CONTINUING EDUCATION

Time Series Methods for Risk Analysis, Barcelona School of Econ. (20 hrs.)	Feb. 28-Mar.11, 2022
Stata Conference 2020, Stata Corp. (12 hrs.)	Jul. 30-31, 2020
Machine Learning and Data Science for Economists, NABE (14 hrs.)	Feb. 28-Mar.1, 2018
Communication and Presentation Skills Seminar, NABE (14 hrs.)	Oct. 1-2, 2014
Applied Econometrics Certificate Program, NABE (21 hrs.)	Aug. 18-21, 2014
Chartered Financial Analyst, CFA Institute (~ 900 hrs.)	Aug. 2013
Economic Measurement Seminar, NABE (14 hrs.)	Jul. 25-26, 2011
Graduate Summer School, London School of Economics, London, U.K. ($\sim 50~\mathrm{hr}$	rs.) Jul. 2000

PUBLICATIONS

"The importance of business owners in assessing the size of precautionary savings," (with E. Hurst, A. Lusardi, and A. Kennickell) *Review of Economics and Statistics*, 92(1), February 2010, 61-69. doi.org/10.1162/rest.2009.11500 (Longer version: www.nber.org/papers/w11731.)

HONORS AND AWARDS

Banco de España Graduate Studies Scholarship	2004 - 2006
Fundación Caja Madrid Graduate Studies Scholarship	2002 - 2004
Fundación FUNCAS Graduate Studies Scholarship	2001 - 2002